[wind whistling]
[baby crying]
[clattering]
[thunder rumbling]
[tense dramatic music playing]
[bell ringing]
[music intensifies]
[narrator] At that prodigious instant.
Melquiades' final keys were revealed
to Aureliano Babilonia.
He saw the epigraph of the parchments
perfectly placed
in the order of man's time and space.
The first of the line is tied to a tree.
and the last is being eaten by ants.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
[footsteps approaching]
[tense music playing]
[narrator] At the center
of the chalk circle only he could enter.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía decided
with brief and unappealable orders
the fate of the world.
[distant shouting]
- [man] Colonel?
- Hmm?
There are some women outside
that wanna talk to you.
Well. let 'em wait.
[woman 1] This is a peaceful protest!
- Aureliano José?
- Yes. sir?
Where are my tweezers?
[women chanting] Release General Moncada!
Release General Moncada!
[chanting continues]
[chanting subsides]
[woman 2] Moncada is innocent!
Set him free!
[woman 1] Release him!
Ladies.
you are all violating curfew.
Go home already.
You've taken back Macondo. Aureliano.
Why is that not enough for you?
If you've got something else
that you'd like to say.
then file a formal petition
with the Council of War.
Good afternoon.
You can talk down to us all you want.
But don't you forget. Aureliano.
that as long as God keeps me
on this earth. I'm your mother.
And no matter how revolutionary you are.
I can still pull down your pants
and give you a proper whipping
if I have to!
Release General Moncada!
[chanting] Release General Moncada!
- Release General Moncada!
- Right.
Release General Moncada!
[chanting continues]
[woman 1] Stop pushing me!
[man 1] Hey. stop pushing. ladies!
- [woman 1] Release him!
- [man 1] Stop it!
[man 2] Is your fear of death so great
that you can't even speak to a man
who's been condemned to it?
[Úrsula] Release him right now!
[man 1] Ma'am. stop resisting.
or we're gonna arrest you too!
[woman 3] You monster!
[man 3] That's enough! That's enough!
Everybody go home!
That's right.
Look me in the eyes
before you take my life.
Make no mistake. José Raquel.
I did not sentence you.
The revolution sentenced you.
Go to hell. Aureliano.
You know as well as I do
that these war councils are a farce.
Hmm. Let me ask you this.
Wouldn't you have done
the same thing in my place?
Probably.
Yeah.
But this isn't about my execution.
The thing that really concerns me
is that. for how much you say
you despise the military.
you've become just like them.
- [Aureliano] Hmm.
- Mm.
[uneasy music playing]
[whistle blows]
[man] Citizens of Macondo!
[two whistle blasts]
[man] A curfew is in place across town.
No one is allowed to go outside.
Where are you going at this hour?
[man] There will be no exceptions!
To see the execution.
Didn't you hear? There's curfew.
Do you want to come?
- Why would you wanna see that?
- [whistle blows]
That's how our father died.
[narrator] José Arcadio Segundo
and Aureliano Segundo
looked like a trick of mirrors.
They were so much alike
that not even Santa Sofía de la Piedad.
their mother. could tell them apart.
[uneasy music continues]
[man 2] Soldiers!
Ready!
[rifles cock]
[woman] Our Father. who art in heaven.
hallowed be thy name.
Thy kingdom come. thy will be done
on earth as it is in heaven.
[man 2] Aim!
[music intensifies]
- [man 2] Fire!
- [gunshots]
- [distant gunshot]
- [gasps]
[gunshot]
- [José Arcadio II] He's alive! He's alive.
- [man 2] Soldiers. take him away!
- [man 3] Hey. stop him!
- He's still alive!
[man 3] It's the colonel's nephew.
[José Arcadio II] He's still alive!
- [man 2] Grab him!
- You're gonna bury him alive!
- Come on.
- Murderer!
[man 2] Restrain him!
Stop moving!
- [man 2] Take him away!
- Stop!
- He's alive! He's alive!
- Let's go. Come on.
[José Arcadio II] Murderers!
You're gonna bury him alive!
He's still alive!
[melancholy music playing]
[José Arcadio II] You're all murderers!
[breathing heavily]
[melancholy music continues]
[bell ringing]
[narrator] The death of General Moncada
made such an impression
on José Arcadio Segundo
that from then on. he detested war.
and he decided to take refuge
in the town church.
[women whisper prayers]
[father] We are gathered here today
to pay tribute to a great man.
whom God has called back
to his kingdom this morning.
General José Raquel Moncada.
[man 1] God didn't call him. Father.
He was murdered
by those god-forsaken Liberals.
- [man 2] That's right.
- The colonel killed him!
[man 3] The colonel's a murderer!
[man 4] He's a murderer!
Silence. all of you!
We are still in the house of God.
not in some public square.
[tense music playing]
[narrator] Meanwhile.
while lost in a book he'd found.
Aureliano Segundo
instantly recognized Melquiades.
Hello. young man.
[narrator] The old gypsy was a memory
that had been passed down
from generation to generation
and had reached him
through his grandfather.
What is this?
[narrator] From then on.
they met every afternoon.
Melquiades spoke to him of the world.
He tried to impress upon him
his old wisdom
but refused to translate the manuscripts.
for their meaning was not to be understood
until a hundred years had passed.
[music fades]
[woman] Sir. could you help me?
[man] Of course. What do you need?
[woman] May I please have five of these?
[music turns ominous]
[woman 1] You wouldn't believe
how much they've grown.
[woman 2] See you both tomorrow. then?
[woman 1] We'll be there nice and early
so we can discuss.
- [woman 2] Mm-hmm.
- See you.
[tense percussive music playing]
"And it is my honor
to continue to strengthen the ties
that make us proud
to belong to this corner of the world."
Who writes this bullshit?
[clears throat]
You put sugar in this?
[Aureliano José] Father. what's wrong?
[clears throat]
[grunting]
[Aureliano José] Hey. what is it?
- Help!
- [man] What is it? What happened?
- Breathe. breathe!
- [Gerineldo] Medic!
- Breathe!
- [man] Colonel. what's wrong?
- [man 2] We need a medic!
- Colonel!
[somber music playing]
Mama Úrsula. Aureliano's been poisoned!
[music turns percussive]
Santa Sofía. fetch me a basket of eggs
and vinegar and two sprigs of dill.
[dark ethereal music playing]
[Úrsula] Leave me alone with my son.
Why are you still standing there?
- [man] Come on.
- [Gerineldo] Let's go.
[painful groan]
[groaning]
[gulping]
[groans]
[Aureliano continues groaning]
[Aureliano coughs. vomits]
[panting. groaning]
[ominous music playing]
[music fades]
[door lock clicks]
[narrator] Remedios the Beauty
had wandered naked through the house
for 20 years…
Go put some clothes on.
…because her nature
would not accept any form of convention.
Aureliano José. forgive her.
She won't stop. It's a bad habit.
It's not a habit. Mama. It's too hot.
[Sofía] How's your father?
Grandma's still with him.
They gave him enough strychnine
to put a horse down.
but Úrsula says he'll survive.
Amen. I can get your room ready
if you'd like to spend the night.
No. No. thank you.
Just picking something up.
Are my things still here?
Mama Úrsula won't let us touch anything.
She's still holding out hope
that you'll come to your senses soon.
Excuse me.
Go ahead.
[narrator] Aureliano José knew then
what he had to do
because he was no longer some child
afraid of the dark.
but an animal of the barracks.
[Amaranta] Who is it?
Amaranta. it's me.
Let me in.
[both moaning]
No. wait.
Sh. Listen to me. all right?
I met a Liberal colonel in battle.
and I told him about me and you.
I always knew you were reckless!
I told him I wanted to marry my aunt.
You're not just reckless. you're a fool!
He said that's the whole reason
we're at war with the Church.
[Amaranta grunts]
I did everything
aside from breastfeeding you.
Raised you like you were my son.
So get out.
I really mean it this time.
Aureliano José.
And don't come back.
Or I'll kill myself.
[tense percussive music playing]
[distant chattering]
[suspenseful music playing]
[man in distance] It's our night tonight.
Let's win this thing tonight.
It's our night tonight.
[narrator] No one knew exactly
when José Arcadio Segundo
began ringing the bells
in the church tower
or started assisting
Father Antonio Isabel at Mass
and tending the fighting cocks
in the parish courtyard.
But he became as skilled
in theological tricks
as he was in the tricks of cockfighting.
- [organ music playing]
- [indistinct chattering]
Let 'em loose!
[men cheering]
[indistinct shouting]
[Antonio Isabel] Kill him! Kill him!
Come on!
[music fades]
[Aureliano] Thank you. Mother.
You'll stay in Macondo
until you're fully recovered?
[Aureliano groans]
In that case. may God be with you. son.
[distant chattering]
[groans]
Gentlemen. get ready. [groans]
We're leaving today. Same as we planned.
I'm sorry if I'm overstepping.
but you should rest for a few days.
my friend.
[Aureliano] I've decided to appoint you
civil and military leader.
Macondo needs someone trustworthy.
And I need you to take care of
the sons of bitches that tried to kill me.
Where's my son?
- Where is Aureliano José?
- I don't know. I haven't seen him.
[Aureliano] Hmm.
Anyone who's unwilling
to join the revolution
has no place with us.
[man 1] Bartender. bring us a bottle.
Two for my friends.
[trumpet music playing]
[indistinct chattering]
- [man 2] This is important.
- [man 3] No!
[man 4] Hey. what's going on?
[chattering continues indistinctly]
- [man 5] You heard about the colonel?
- [man 6] Oh. yeah. They almost killed him.
[man 5] What about you two?
Give 'em four more. Four more.
[man 2] I'm telling you.
his days are numbered.
[man 6] What did you say
about the colonel?
I'm just here for a drink.
No. no. me too. I was just asking.
Always the same shit with this guy.
- Macondo is Liberal!
- [people gasp]
What's wrong with you?
I hope to God they kill the colonel!
- Kill him once and for all!
- [man 8] This is our town!
Liberal motherfuckers!
- [man 7] You're all murderers!
- [man 8] Liberal trash!
- [man 9] Conservative bastards!
- We'll show you who's weak.
[man 8] I'll kill you. I swear to God!
Get off of me!
[man 4] I'm gonna kill you!
That's right! I'm here!
Right here! Come on!
[man 5] I'll kill you!
[music intensifies]
[man 7] You want some more? Come on!
I'll take you all! Come on!
[men grunting]
[glass shatters]
[music fades]
[sniffles]
[breathing heavily]
- [screams]
- [glass shatters]
[dogs barking]
[Aureliano José screams]
[sniffles]
[chimes ringing]
[rooster crows]
Here.
[Aureliano José] Thank you.
Why am I here?
Should I have left you to sleep outside?
Got another one?
Take this one.
[narrator] Pilar Ternera
had lost all semblance of hope.
yet her heart
never turned bitter with age.
Over time. they became more
than mother and son.
They became accomplices in solitude.
MARCONI TELEGRAPH
[accordion music playing]
DON'T BE DUMB.
RAIN IS NORMAL IN AUGUST.
The Conservative army
has not advanced yet.
Situation under control in Macondo.
[narrator] As the appointed
civil and military leader of Macondo.
Gerineldo had telegraphic conversations
with Colonel Aureliano Buendía
twice a week.
[Aureliano] Colonel Márquez.
We're extremely close
to the Sierra Nevada.
War never lets up.
but surely our sacrifices will bear fruit.
There's no time
for weakness or hesitation.
Sincerely. Colonel Aureliano Buendía.
[Gerineldo] Your family is doing well.
Úrsula remains as strong as ever.
still selling her candy all over town.
[narrator] But little by little.
the dots and dashes of his voice
became faint and distant.
Aureliano. it's raining in Macondo.
Don't be stupid. Gerineldo.
Rain is not unusual in Macondo in August.
[thunder rumbling]
[music fades]
May the grace of our Lord. Jesus Christ.
be with you always.
[congregation] And also with you.
[in Latin] In the name of the Father.
and of the Son. and of the Holy Spirit.
[congregation] Amen.
[Antonio Isabel] You may be seated.
Today. we will offer
the Sacrifice of the Mass
so that the discord
that has arisen among us
over the faith of Christ
may come to an end.
Because our lives are but fleeting
and full of sorrow.
according to Solomon.
in the Book of Wisdom.
Our lives are but fleeting
and full of sorrow.
and there is no consolation for a man
when he reaches his end.
nor after his death. for never has a man
been known to return from the grave.
Remedios. for the love of God!
Where is your shawl?
What did you do with your shawl?
[Antonio Isabel] Our Father.
who art in heaven. hallowed be thy name.
[indistinct chattering]
[knocking at door]
[Úrsula] Amaranta. for God's sake.
why won't you open the door?
Mrs. Buendía.
My name is Asunción Centeno.
and this is my son.
There's no need
to say anything else. ma'am.
I recognize that look.
Amaranta. bring me my notebook.
[poignant piano music playing]
[intriguing music playing]
[narrator] Children of every age
and skin color continued to arrive.
Every single one of them male.
They all bore the same look of solitude
that revealed their kinship.
They were all baptized
with the name Aureliano
and their mother's surname.
as the law did not allow them
to take their father's surname
until he recognized them.
[music fades]
I'll need you to bring
four bottles of rum from the sacristy.
There's only one left.
They drank them all last night.
Then we'll have
communion wine today. [chuckles]
[woman] Hello!
Morning.
Oh. Father. I'm sorry to show up
unannounced like this.
but I'm wondering if you could help.
Someone told me you are kind.
Nice to meet you.
Petra Cotes. Just arrived in Macondo.
Father Antonio Isabel.
I wanted to know if you would be so kind
as to let me raffle my rabbits tonight.
At one of your famous cockfights.
That depends on which political party
you're affiliated with. Petra.
[whimsical music playing]
Father. God's political party. of course!
[chuckles]
[Antonio Isabel]
Then come tonight at 8:00.
[music stops]
May God bless you. Father.
[chuckles]
[indistinct chattering]
[man 1] Kill him. you stupid bird!
What am I betting for. you useless animal!
That's it! Come on. come on!
[Aureliano José] Ten pesos on Torbellino.
What are you doing here?
I'm betting.
That a problem?
If they catch you here.
they'll have you thrown out.
This is the house of God.
and everyone here is welcome.
[Antonio Isabel] Let them loose!
[men shouting. cheering]
Twenty to fifteen on Pinto. Let's bet!
- Isn't that the colonel's son?
- Come on. bird! Come on! Peck!
Peck him. Torbellino!
What are you doing?
Let go. José Arcadio! Let go of me!
You put your hands on me again.
I'll break your fucking face.
That's the colonel's son.
Get him out of here!
Get rid of that Liberal!
Get out now!
[Aureliano José] All right. all right.
Liberals are not permitted in here.
Who says I'm a Liberal?
I just wanted to place a bet.
Look. just go to Catarino's or go home.
You're piss drunk.
Since when are you a Conservative?
Huh?
And why have you been hiding
your girlfriend. huh?
She's not my girlfriend.
How are you?
Please excuse my nephew.
He doesn't know women yet.
That's why he's such an idiot.
But I know women very well.
[Petra chuckles]
Just go.
Get out of here.
[Aureliano José] José Arcadio.
Here's to finding love!
[door opens. closes]
[sighs]
[tense percussive music playing]
[José Arcadio II] Three.
Four.
Five.
Six.
Seven.
Eight.
[panting]
[José Arcadio II moaning]
Nine. ten.
- [music stops]
- [relieved sigh]
[tense percussive music resumes]
[moaning]
[moaning intensifies]
- [gunshot]
- [Aureliano gasps]
[panicked grunts]
[Aureliano breathing heavily]
- [music fades]
- [horse whinny]
[man in distance] Easy! Easy! Whoa!
Carnicero!
[sighs]
[indistinct chattering in distance]
What news do you have?
An emissary from the capital
has got a message from the president.
[Aureliano] Let him in.
One more thing. Bring me a ruana.
It's freezing in here.
[splutters] Good morning. sir.
I. uh… I've I brought you a le…
a letter from the… p-p-president.
You read it.
I'm getting dressed.
[man splutters] "D-D…"
"Dear Au… Aurel--"
Buendía.
[man] "B-Buendía." [chuckles]
[normal] "The nation longs for peace."
[Aureliano snorts]
[man] "I urge you
to consider an armistice."
"In laying down your arms.
the government ensures you a future
where your legacy will be known
not for conflict.
but rather for the heroism
of lasting peace."
[coughs]
[man chuckles]
Dear Mr. President.
Comma.
If I may say so respectfully…
you can go straight to hell
and take your armistice with you.
[tense music stinger]
[sighs]
[tense music playing]
[narrator] Adrift in the loneliness
of his immeasurable power.
he began to lose his way.
His orders were carried out
before they were ever given.
before he had conceived them.
And they always went much further
than what he intended.
[street vendor] Get your paper!
All your regional and capital news here!
[woman] I'll take one. Felipe.
[Felipe] Get your paper!
[uneasy music playing]
[woman] I've got vegetables.
fruit. onions…
"Aureliano Buendía…
[street vendors shouting indistinctly]
…the subversive group leader
in the Caribbean.
unleashes violence and sends
macabre message to the president."
[somber music playing]
[man] "There's reason to believe
that it was Colonel Buendía himself
who decapitated the emissary.
thus sending his grim message
to the president of the republic."
[music fades]
[Pilar] "His message.
an utter rejection of an armistice.
has shocked the entire country."
- Aureliano.
- Hmm?
You shouldn't go out tonight.
There's gonna be trouble
after this thing with your father.
Don't worry.
I'm just going to the theater.
There's someone I want you to meet.
Oh yeah? Who?
Stay here.
I'll set up a time for you to meet her.
I promise I'll be home early.
I'll meet her then.
[dramatic string music playing]
[sighs]
Tomorrow. we leave for Asturias.
Portugal. who once gave us asylum.
will grant us safe passage.
Till tomorrow. then.
Sleep well. Sleep. my friend.
Sir. will you keep vigil over my sleep?
From now on.
you and I are one and the same.
- But. sir…
- Leave me be until dawn.
There I have lost all that I have loved.
- [actor 1] So have I.
- So have I.
[actor 2] Fathers. brothers…
- [man] Sh.
- [actor 1] I've been betrayed too.
- [actor 2] I had to flee.
[actor 1] I expect nothing.
Neither do I.
[actor 2] At times. I think about
horrible acts of revenge.
- Is that dagger yours?
- Yes.
[actor 3] That dagger shall be
the death of Conservatives.
- [actor 2] I'm Conservative!
- So am I!
- [whistles]
- [man] Sh!
- [woman] Stop whistling. Be quiet!
- [man 2] Be quiet.
[actors grunting]
[applause]
[cheering]
You know I've never been to the theater.
Me neither. We'll come back soon.
Go to hell.
you Conservative son of a bitch!
- [woman 1] Hey. watch out!
- [woman 2] Did you see that?
The only son of a bitch here is you!
[man 1] Hey. don't let him push you
around like that.
[man 2] Yeah. fight!
Let the first stone be cast…
by the man who hasn't fucked
his own whore of a mother.
[woman 3] Don't talk about
his mother that way!
Mess with my mother.
and I'll put a bullet in you!
- Conservative bastard!
- Show him who's in charge.
He's more than a son of a bitch.
He's a Buendía.
- [man 3] Out with the Buendías!
- Put that Liberal scum in his place.
Firstborn of the filthiest bastard
this town's ever seen.
[crowd shouting indistinctly]
[both grunting]
[crowd shouting. whistling]
[crowd gasps]
[narrator] Carmelita Montiel.
a twenty-year-old virgin.
had just bathed in orange blossom water.
She was scattering rosemary leaves
on Pilar Ternera's bed
when the shot went off.
[gunshot]
[man 1] Grab that son of a bitch! Get him!
[man 2] Don't let that bastard get away!
[man 3] Kill that Conservative
son of bitch!
[crowd clamoring]
[somber music playing]
[narrator] Aureliano José
had been destined to find with her
the happiness that Amaranta
had denied him.
To have seven children
and to die in her arms of old age.
[gunshots]
[narrator] The other man's body
was so far gone
that a patrol had to use a wheelbarrow
to carry away his remains.
which had fallen apart
like bread soaked in water.
[in Latin] May his soul rest in peace.
In the name of the Father.
and of the Son. and of the Holy Spirit.
[in English] Rest in peace. my son.
[Úrsula sobs]
HUMAN VANITIES END HERE
- [somber music continues]
- [rain pattering]
[narrator] Months later.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía
returned to Macondo
after committing
inconceivable acts of cruelty
to quell his own officers' rebellion.
[thunder rumbling]
[narrator] He arrived in silence
and without an escort.
wrapped in a blanket. despite the heat.
exhausted by the uncertainty
and the vicious circle of the endless war.
which always brought him back
to the same place.
Only older. wearier.
and no closer to knowing why.
how. or even when.
[music fades]
It doesn't bother you
to share a table with a killer?
Thank you.
His own son was murdered because of him.
Don't say that. Aureliano José was--
He was murdered in vengeance
for the colonel's atrocities.
They murdered him…
because war is always more unfair
to the innocent.
But all wars are like that.
That's a list of
all of your other sons' names.
Seventeen have come knocking so far.
[intriguing music playing]
[narrator] The colonel then realized
that the young boys and teenagers
he saw everywhere.
that looked at him with his own eyes.
were the children he had fathered
with women whose names he did not know.
[Gerineldo] Aureliano.
How are you. son?
[Gerineldo] We got word from the capital
that you had come back to Macondo.
They sent another emissary.
There are lawyers here to see you.
[man 1] Mr. Buendía.
We've come on behalf of the president.
I know why you're here.
Let's get to the point.
[man 1] Right.
The president reiterates his commitment
to grant you political participation
in all the towns you have liberated
in exchange for these three things.
- [Aureliano] I'm listening.
- All right.
First and foremost.
you must immediately renounce
any review of existing property titles.
Secondly. you must renounce the fight
against clerical influence.
And finally. you must renounce
the aspirations of equal rights
between natural and illegitimate children
to preserve and protect
household integrity.
So what you're saying is
that for the last 20 years.
we've been fighting
for nothing more than power.
[scoffs]
Then show me where to sign.
Pen. please.
Here. Mr. Buendía. Here. Sign here.
Excuse me. Colonel. but this is treason.
[tense music playing]
What did you just say. Gerineldo?
That by signing this armistice
you renounce everything we've fought for.
And that makes you a traitor.
Go say goodbye to your mother.
From this point forward.
you will have to answer
to the Council of War.
Take care of your heart. Aureliano.
because it's been rotting for years.
my friend.
[door swings]
[music fades]
I know you plan to execute Gerineldo.
And there's nothing I can do to stop you.
But mark my words. Aureliano.
the moment I see his body.
I swear to you that.
on my father and my mother's bones…
and on the memory of José Arcadio Buendía…
I swear before God. Aureliano.
that I will find you.
no matter where you go.
and I will kill you with my own hands.
The same way I would have done…
if you'd come into the world
with a pig's tail.
[sobs]
[door opens]
The farce is over. my friend.
You're a free man.
I'd rather die by firing squad
than see you become a traitor.
Don't worry.
You won't see me become a traitor.
Get out of there
before the mosquitoes eat you alive.
[intriguing music playing]
ARMISTICE SIGNED BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT
AND THE REBEL FORCES
You are better than ever. Colonel.
You could fight 30 more wars.
[Aureliano] Can you show me
exactly where my heart is. Doctor?
Everyone tells me it's rotten.
Allow me.
[music intensifies]
What's all this?
Great-Grandfather's projects.
Did he make these?
Some he did.
but he almost drove Great-Grandma crazy.
Just like how you will
if you keep distracting me.
[narrator] José Arcadio Segundo never knew
that what he found
would change the fate of Macondo.
[knocking at door]
[José Arcadio II] Get the door. Aureliano.
[Aureliano II] Hang on.
[music stops]
Why the long face. José Arcadio?
Let's go celebrate peace.
[narrator] Although people
frequently confused him with his brother.
that day. Aureliano Segundo
didn't correct her.
[mysterious organ music playing]
Good morning. Colonel.
We're glad you could make it.
Listen. before I sign.
I have one final request.
I want to ensure that my men
receive a pension
as the war veterans they are.
and for you to recognize us
as a legitimate army.
That's all I ask for
in exchange for total surrender.
Not to worry. Colonel.
You have my word.
This way.
[music intensifies]
Aureliano.
[tense music playing]
[gunshot echoes]
[music intensifies]
[music fades]
[dramatic music playing]
[mysterious rhythmic music playing]
[music fades]
[dark ethereal music playing]
[ethereal string music playing]
[music fades]